But if we now come back all the way to\h
your question in the beginning, "What\h\h
now determines something as wholesome,\h
or what determines something as\h
unwholesome?", well, that is fully\h
up to you discerning whether your mind\h\h
is pressuring you, and that will be an "internal"\h
criteria. And so even if the whole world says:\h\h
"Wait, what you just did there is wrong", if you\h
know that it wasn't coming out of your mind\h\h
pressuring you, then from the point of view\h
of dhamma it will for you not have been wrong Yesterday
when we were together, you mentioned\h
just briefly about right and wrong;\h\h
about something being right\h
or wrong as quite black or white,\h\h
and I was just curious about what the criteria\h
is for something that's right or wrong, and to kind of...
maybe just clarify as far as I see it
the definition of right is\h
more to do with it not being wrong
that most of the
descriptions in the suttas for example are\h
more about kind of negative, it's not this or\h\h
not that, and it kind of seems that the rightness\h
is more about what you're left with once you've\h\h
removed these kind of wrong views so to\h
establish the right view. I'm just curious if
that seems correct, or if there is\h
actually something more substantial there.\h\h
Well, let's find out. So we were\h
talking yesterday about what\h\h
makes something wholesome and\h
what makes something unwholesome.
Now perhaps to start: there are these famous\h
ovāda pāṭimokkha verses by the Buddha and there\h\h
he starts out by saying: "Refraining from what\h
is unwholesome" and then it says "doing what\h\h
is wholesome" and that particular order there is\h
already significant. So it starts by seeing and\h\h
understanding what is unwholesome and by\h
then gradually understanding that more and more,\h\h
recognizing unwholesome as unwholesome,\h
which has got various layers of subtlety to it,\h\h
you will discern that principle and move\h
towards an understanding of what is wholesome.\h\h
So in your question you're basically right. You\h
come upon that which is wholesome by understanding\h\h
what is unwholesome. And you can see that in the\h
gradual training also, which begins with the virtue,\h\h
which is all about starting out by not doing\h
certain things, which you might have to take on\h\h
faith from the beginning; it might not be completely\h
clear what's now wrong with these things. I mean,\h\h
killing and stealing is ... right? The moral\h
precepts are obviously clear but beyond that,\h\h
what constitutes something as unwholesome? That's now\h
the question, right? So in your own experience,\h\h
how do you know whether a certain action by body\h
speech or mind is
unwholesome and should therefore be avoided. What is\h
the criteria? Are you just going to stick to the\h\h
external rules, to the formulations that you have\h
as a monk? Or if you're a lay person, you're keeping\h\h
a certain number of precepts; you just keep that\h
externally, you understand what is within the rule\h\h
and what is not within the rule? So you just keep\h
the rules and everything else is automatically\h\h
fine? Or is there a more fundamental criteria\h
that determines something as unwholesome?\h\h
What would you say?
Well you would need to start\h
by holding them externally, because
I've heard many times a kind of\h
definition of what might be unwholesome,\h\h
but to think that... or you could just\h
look into the suttas right now and find\h\h
a definition of what is unwholesome. What\h
is a more precise criteria for the answer to the
question, but that doesn't necessarily mean\h
you can find that experience or know that in\h\h
your experience right from the start. But\h
then what what do the suttas say is unwholesome?
Well, acting out of greed, hatred and delusion as\h
a kind of standard. As a kind of standard. Of\h\h
course, that's a textual answer, which is not wrong, but in a sense everybody can say\h\h
that. So, okay. So then in your experience, upholding\h
those precepts, then it would be about discerning
why those things are acting out of greed\h
hatred and delusion, so gradually\h\h
coming closer and closer to understanding\h
what is... yes understanding\h\h
what falls within greed hatred and delusion.\h
Now in your own experience, can you describe\h\h
what would make ... what greed, hatred and let's\h
say muddle-mindedness or delusion, what those\h\h
three have in common, so that you can say: "Wait,\h
that's the wrong direction, that is decline, that\h\h
is deteriorating away from dhamma" and so on?\h
What would that be? What constitutes something\h\h
as greed, as hatred or as muddle-mindedness,\h
all the way from the most coarse to the most subtle?
There's a bunch of things, but one\h
of them is loss of perspective.\h\h
I just get totally caught in my\h
thought, the object of the senses or
whatever is pressuring me at that moment.\h
And there is a pressure to go in\h\h
that direction. It feels I have to\h
go there because otherwise I feel the\h\h
pressure is felt again. It seems like if\h
I don't go there I will suffer.\h\h
It seems like that; seems that if I'm not acting\h
out of those things that pressure me,\h
if I don't go in that direction of where they\h
pressure me, I'm going to suffer. It feels like\h\h
the natural way of going\h
out of that and those kind of things
make me totally lose perspective and\h
lose the context of my situation. I lose\h\h
the sense of what's going on really. So\h
what is the factor there, in all of this that\h\h
you just described? What is the factor based on\h
which you can say "This is unwholesome?" Because\h\h
losing yourself in senses and not having\h
perspective, all of that is already in a sense the\h\h
result of going in that wrong direction.\h
So if you want to let's say go upstream, so\h\h
to speak, and you want to find out\h
which phenomenon in your experience determines
unwholesome as unwholesome,
how would you describe that?
I guess\hit's felt as an
unpleasant pressure and that\h\h
pressure is there because of you craving.
It\hwouldn't necessarily be that obvious.\h
But are you sure this is it?
And craving manifest as pressure?
I'm not saying it's wrong. I'm just asking. I
wouldn't say... I'm not sure if it manifests as\h\h
pressure. But that pressure is there?
Yes,\hexactly. Good, so you find that that pressure\h\h
is there. Then what? If it was that pressure,\h
then I think it would be much easier to kind
of untangle yourself or realize that you're\h
craving. But what if it is that pressure?\h\h
What if acting out of the pressure is the\h
determining factor for unwholesome, even if\h\h
the whole world says "It's fine, there's no problem\h
with it, you can do it", but you clearly see "Wait, my\h\h
mind is just pushing me now..." The pressure is\h
not necessarily in your control? Okay, so\h\h
we can go into that. Then I wouldn't be able\h
to free myself. Wait. Okay, but now that's a\h\h
bit of a jump. We're just first finding out...\h
so there's the pressure...  right? Now,\h\h
what if you don't act out of that pressure?\h
You're aware that your mind is pushing you\h\h
in a certain direction, pressuring you, you\h
recognize the pressure and you make sure that\h\h
you're not acting out of it by body speech and by\h
mind? Are you then doing anything unwholesome?
No. No. That's right, even though that pressure is\h
there. Yes, right. So the unwholesome action, which\h\h
is always on you, starts when you are acting out\h
of that pressure and it's now important to realize\h\h
that in fact your mind cannot force you to do\h
certain things; you will always be there giving\h\h
in and going along with the pressure, and that is\h
eventually how you come to recognize the safety\h\h
from unwholesome, because precisely because it's\h
always up to you, you can develop yourself so as\h\h
to not give in to the pressure, so that even in the\h
face of pressure you will not be doing anything
unwholesome. Which is why we often talk about\h
the importance of having that attitude\h\h
of responsibility and fundamentally that\h
is what the right view then boils down to.\h\h
It is seeing beyond doubt what is your\h
responsibility and what isn't. So acting out\h\h
by body speech and mind of that pressure is what\h
constitutes unwholesome action, but not the mere\h\h
presence of the pressure. But if you now overshoot\h
it and say: "Well, I don't want to have that pressure",\h\h
you would just go to the other extreme and you now\h
start basically attacking your own mind, assuming\h\h
that it shouldn't be pressuring you, that you don't\h
want to be pressured, which is ironically now you\h\h
acting out of ill will towards your own mind. That\h
is why we often speak about right endurance. That\h\h
pressure is there which is in a sense not directly of your making. It's there\h\h
due to stuff that you've done in the past, but\h
now you are stuck with it, so then you just have\h\h
to endure it and clearly see that distinction:
"Wait, this is mind pressuring me and now it's up\h\h
to me whether I act out of that pressure or not."
And in order to get that distinction clear, that\h\h
is precisely the perspective; the perspective\h
upon your situation. And so if there's pressure\h\h
you cannot fundamentally not do things, so\h
then the wisdom is in learning "Can I do\h\h
things while that pressure is there that are\h
not, let's say, coming out of that pressure?"
Another thing recently I found helpful was
when the mind's pressured and you
know you should really restrain this tendency\h\h
to act out, even if it's not breaking the\h
precepts or it seems quite remote, like kind of what\h\h
you said, beyond the scope of the precepts,
it kind of seems like that. Just not seeing any\h\h
pressure outside the scope of the precepts in a\h
sense. Does that makes sense? Because that
thread is the same, and that if you feed,
if you feed the mind now then and you keep going\h\h
in that same direction then eventually you would\h
break precepts, even if it's going for a walk
or muddling with or getting tangled up with doubt.\h
Still it's the same trajectory.
So it's a fault of... I don't know.
I'm not sure if I follow, but if by keeping\h\h
the precepts... Look, the whole point of keeping those\h
precepts is for you to even begin to recognize\h\h
what it means to be pressured by the mind, right? Because the starting point is that you'll\h\h
just be running with it, so you don't even see it.\h
Then you have various good reasons for keeping the\h\h
precepts, you keep them and so at some point your\h
mind wants to push you in that direction, but now\h\h
you being committed to those precepts say: "Wait\h
I don't want to go there." So there's going to be\h\h
somewhat of an "internal" conflict\h
between your mind pushing you in one direction,\h\h
then at some point you run against that fence,\h
which is those precepts that you're keeping. Now\h\h
those precepts, they are in your welfare if you\h
don't break them, but more fundamentally, their\h\h
point is that when you run\h
into the fence you want to say "Wait, why am I even\h\h
running in this direction?" and so you turn around\h
and you see "Aha! It was basically my mind\h\h
pressuring me" and that begins with those eight\h
precepts. And then getting that principle you want\h\h
to refine it more and more, so that you see more\h
clearly your mind pressuring you. That's the whole\h\h
point of those precepts. And that example that you\h
mentioned with that monk who is just not doing\h\h
anything unwholesome by body speech and mind,\h
if you see to that degree with such clarity your\h\h
own mind and whether it pressures you or not, then\h
you don't need any of those rules. You can just\h\h
not act... then anything that comes out of that\h
pressure will be unwholesome and you don't do it.\h\h
But then of course you should be quite clear, so when the Buddha asked that monk "Do you see that?"\h\h
then basically that monk is declaring himself to\h
the Buddha to be a noble disciple, because\h\h
Sāriputta, when he was asked in the sammā diṭṭhi sutta,\h
"How how do we know what is right view?" then the first\h\h
thing Sāriputta mentions is "Well, here a noble disciple knows\h
the wholesome and the root of the wholesome\h\h
and the unwholesome and the root of the unwholesome. This is how someone is of right view." So\h\h
when the Buddha then asks that particular monk "Do\h
you see unwholesome as unwholesome?" and if he\h\h
then says fully "Yes, I see all of that", to the point\h
that I can train and not doing anything unwholesome, he was\h\h
basically already having the right view, so then\h
he was on that middle way; he has understood that\h\h
principle, so then okay, then just develop it. But we should\h
not be taking any liberties. It's better to
to be on the safe side. Start with those precepts\h
and then as we discussed now earlier, within that,\h\h
within those boundaries you begin to refine it, but\h
at the end of the day it is between you and your\h\h
mind, and when that relationship is fully clear (i.e.\h
mind pressuring you) and you can say that greed\h\h
hate and illusion or hindrances are just particular\h
manifestations of the same pressure, that's what\h\h
they all have in common. That relationship you\h
want to fully clear up. And then you do not depend\h\h
on anyone in the world, on anything "external" to tell you what's right and wrong, because\h\h
the only criteria for whether you do something\h
or not is whether your own mind is pressuring\h\h
you in that direction which is unwholesome, or\h
whether it's not. And then there's no issue with it.\h\h
And then wherever you are, you\h
keeping an eye on what your own mind is doing,\h\h
whether it is pressing you or not, you will be able\h
to practice in every situation regardless. Now it's\h\h
still better to be in seclusion, because it will\hbe
much more easy to recognize these things. So if\h\h
you sleep a lot, if you have a lot of duties, people\h
around, work to do, talking, and so on... you eat too\h\h
much,  you become sleepy... right? Then that will all\h
be an impediment to keeping an eye on what that\h\h
citta is up to. But the whole principle of wholesome\h
and the root of the wholesome and the\h\h
unwholesome and the root of the unwholesome boils\h
down to that. But in order to even begin to see\h\h
what is going on, you need to start by keeping\h
those precepts and then the gradual training also\h\h
says: sense restraint. Because to even discern\h
what that mind is up to, that is in a sense in the\h\h
opposite direction of being now lost in the world\h
of the senses. That mind will always be peripheral\h\h
and so you cannot attend to it directly, right? This\h
is all the talks about peripheral awareness, seeing\h\h
it indirectly, and so on. What you see directly will\h
always be objects of the senses which is why sense\h\h
restraint - so not losing the perspective and just\h
being lost in objects, but bringing it back, sort\h\h
of "here" - will be necessary, because if\h
you're just lost that way you're not even going to\h\h
see what that mind is doing. And of course, it's\h
that same mind pushing you to be lost there, so\h\h
that it stays out of sight, which is how it has\h
maximum control over you. So if you want to keep\h\h
an eye on it so that you are not the slave of your\h
own mind, but your mind becomes your best ally, you\h\h
have to first pull yourself out from being lost\h
in the domain of the senses, which is why after the\h\h
basic virtue, which will already save you a lot of\h
trouble, sense restraint will be the next thing.
And the right development of yoniso manasikāra is of course\h
what's going to be the next step, because acting\h\h
out of hindrances and attending from the origin,\h
that's mutually exclusive. So by understanding\h\h
what yoniso manasikāra is and developing that, you\h
will be gaining a clearer perspective on what the\h\h
hindrances are and what is pressuring you. But also,\h
we've discussed that quite a few times,\h
just to keep the precepts and not act out and\h
refine that principle that we started to talk\h\h
about in the beginning, is already developing\h
that yoniso direction, whether you call it that or
not. But if we now come back all the way to\h
your question in the beginning, like "What\h\h
now determines something as wholesome\h
or what determines something as\h\h
wholesome" well, that is fully\h
up to you discerning whether your mind\h\h
is pressuring you and that will be an "internal"\h
criteria. And so even if the whole world says\h\h
"Wait, what you just did there is wrong", if you\h
know that it wasn't coming out of your mind\h\h
pressuring you, then from the point of view\h
of dhamma it will for you not have been wrong.
That's kind of amazing.
At the beginning it's threatening, and then it\h\h
becomes... Well, because true freedom is\h
in the beginning very threatening.
And that sense of independence. And they go\h
together, right? Freedom, responsibility, all\h\h
those things, they're just different\h
facets of the same thing. So to say that you\h\h
are fully responsible for everything you do\h
by body, speech and mind, that statement has\h\h
got meaning only if you see that in relation\h
to your mind pressuring you. If you leave that\h\h
whole domain out then you can say "Yes, I take\h
responsibility for what I do", but that would\h\h
just be a hollow statement if in reality it is\h
your mind pushing you in this and that direction.\h\h
Then it doesn't mean anything. Because it's\h
like "Oh I'm responsible, but I have... I don't have\h\h
the choice but to react to that pressure". It's like,\h
well then you're not responsible at all. Yes, so\h\h
then you can say "I'm responsible", but that's just a joke then. So you have\h\h
to include that and then start training and taming\h
that mind, so that then at some point you\h\h
will be able to start telling that mind what to\h
do, right? In the beginning it's going to be a bit\h\h
of a struggle. You have to tame and train that\h
mind and it might not immediately listen. That\h\h
is why you need to be patient and so on. But at\h
some point that mind begins to trust you, you can\h\h
see "Wait, mind begins to be tamed" that relationship\h
develops and you begin to realize that the\h\h
safety is in your mind not being able to make you\h
do things without you giving in, so it is fully up\h\h
to you and then you realize: "Well, then the whole\h
training is to train that mind", so that it is no\h\h
longer pressuring me in unwholesome directions,\h
but it will see for itself that it is much better\h\h
if it calms down and then you can just live\h
happily together and your mind will be your ally\h\h
rather than something that you need to keep an\h
eye on because if you don't, you'll end up being in\h\h
trouble. Is that freedom from remorse? That kind of...\h
because it's an aspect of it. Not the whole thing.\h\h
Yes, so why are you in remorse about things?\h
What does the remorse depend upon? Well, giving in\h\h
to the pressure. And then on a later occasion\h
realizing: "Wait, that's not right." Yes, knowing\h\h
it's not right. So there has to be some loss of\h
perspective somewhere. And then afterwards\h\h
you sort of regain it and you say: "Well that was\h
now no good." So that is even more reason to keep\h\h
an eye on that mind. Sort of what you what you\h
thought was a form of safety clearly wasn't a\h\h
form of safety. Yes. So that remorse can then also\h
be a clear indicator that there's more work to be\h\h
done. That is why it is good to keep questioning\h
and even in the suttas, for noble disciples that\h\h
is a recurring training like, you know "Can\h
my companions find fault with my conduct?" and\h\h
even that is then just in relation to external\h
things, to stuff that other people can see. Even\h\h
that is still a reflection there. Then how\h
much more so in relation to your\h\h
own thoughts that you might still be delighting\h
in and welcoming.
That was something I've...
been interested in because there's actually quite a lot in the suttas,\h\h
and definitely a lot in the vinaya that\h
is clearly aiming at removing...\h\h
a remorse that might\h
come from quite kind of arbitrary things.
Just about how your etiquette, or how a monk should\h
walk. And there's a lot of advice\h\h
on that, which is doesn't necessarily... if\h
you just had that you wouldn't necessarily be\h\h
pointed in the right direction\h
of your intention. Yes, so I'm not exactly sure\h\h
which ones you are now referring to, but sure, so\h
that there is a level of etiquette and okay, then\h\h
you don't maybe want to be misrepresenting other\h
monks with certain behaviors,
but you see, then fundamentally, still... It seems like it would\h
still be beneficial, because it wouldn't be there.
So you can take that on,\h
consider it, put it into practice, but again,\h\h
now don't just regard that as external, but\h
you can still try to see: "Could there\h\h
be something unwholesome about those things?"
Would there be some restlessness in the mind, or\h\h
something else that is not proper for somebody who\h
is like fully composed and self-controlled, right?\h\h
If you walk down the street on alms round and\h
you are just window shopping, right?\h\h
Just looking at what's on sale... if you still have interest\h\h
in those things, you're sort of missing the point\h
in terms of your overall perspective. Or if you\h\h
are talking loudly, or you're just laughing and\h
joking, then all of that is perhaps\h\h
not too complicated to see that if\h
you want to train yourself on the level of which\h\h
thoughts you are welcoming and not welcoming, but\h
then outwardly you are laughing and joking to\h\h
the point that other people in the street actually...\h
you draw attention from those people; well,\h\h
you cannot be behaving in that way and at the same\h
time keep an eye on what's going on mentally. So\h\h
that's the same reason why seclusion is\h
beneficial. You don't need to talk to anyone\h\h
and if you do not need to talk and break out into\h
speech, it will be much easier to see your mental\h\h
chatter. It's not so easy to see your mental chatter when\h
you're talking the whole time. You don't see it.\h\h
And in fact,  just to\h
break out into speech and say something can of\h\h
course also come out of that same pressure from\h
the mind. So that's the same training: "Should I now\h\h
say this or not?" And we did a whole talk on right\h
speech in the past, and it's that same\h\h
principle. Whether something is wholesome or
unwholesome is not determined by what you say, but by\h\h
the intention based on which you say it. And if you\h
feel pressure to say something then that is what\h\h
makes it unwholesome, not the words that\h
you are saying. Even though when the suttas then say,\h
"Okay, if speech\h
goes in this direction will always be wrong" just\h\h
as breaking precepts will always be wrong, you cannot\h\h
justify breaking those precepts and then say: "Yeah,\h
well, there wasn't any pressure." That's impossible. So\h\h
those outer boundaries are there just to show\h
you the main principle and then it's up to\h\h
you, now develop that same principle\h
that's now coming into sight on account of you\h\h
being committed to those precepts by body and speech, and then\hyou just fully apply it to the mental level as well.
And that is training.\h
And that takes also reviewing. And it's good to\h\h
just make time for that at the end of the day and\h
consider: "Which conversation did I have? What did I\h\h
talk about? Do I still recollect acting\h
out of pressure? And to just get in the habit of\h\h
reflecting in that way and then over\h
time it will become easier to catch yourself\h\h
while you are in that situation, because that is\h
fundamentally where the restraint then needs to\h\h
happen. I think, to go back\h
to the remorse and what you say now is that,\h
this practice of what just you\h
just mentioned... kind of recollecting what\h\h
kind of action, what kind of speech and eventually\h
what kind of thought I was cultivating during the\h\h
day is like basically to kind of cultivate a\h
sense of shame. Tcultivate the right sense\h\h
of shame. And remorse doesn't happen automatically.\h
It's just kind of forgetting literally this\h\h
very sense of shame, because if I was shameful\h
enough this action, I would have actually avoided.\h\h
And basically now I'm ashamed of
lacking enough shame, so I just act out\h\h
of shamelessness really, and I just act out in\h
those ways and that's why it feels like difficult,\h\h
because now I have to kind of recollect and feel\h
that shame, it has to be felt like and that's\h\h
painful and it has to be felt without trying\h
to get rid of it or, and certainly not justifying\h\h
it. Just kind of feeling it and make the\h
determination, say: "Okay, next time I won't do it",\h\h
but now I did so I have to endure the things and I\h
think that's why those practicse are\h\h
so beneficial, but at the same time kind of\h
hard, because you have to endure the\h\h
things over and over again and this\h
attitude of justifying the mind, the\h\h
mind trying to find justification and things like\h
that; it seems much more easy, but that's the very\h\h
reason why, because I was justifying myself. That's\h
the very reason why I give into those actions that\h\h
now I feel shameful of. So I think it kind\h
of also follows like what you were saying before,
it's black and white. You cannot do both at the\h
same time. Whether I cultivate the sense\h\h
of shame or I just: "That's okay, that's all right."\h
You either cover it; you're either covering it\h\h
or you are learning to see... And that is also\h
why it is for a noble disciple one\h\h
of the first faculties that the Buddha often\h
talks about: shame, so the right\h\h
shame, based on the correct understanding, and now\h
the fear of wrongdoing; right fear of wrongdoing,\h\h
like not wanting to now start agitating that mind\h
that you basically were taming. So yes, that's\h\h
good. And and it even says in the context of monks\h
and their precepts, even if you
break one of those precepts - I mean, it's better to\h
not do do that, but if you, let's\h\h
say, break one of those precepts - then to correct them, to realize that you made a\h\h
mistake, confess it, correct it and then determine\h
to not do it again. And then the Buddha says "Yes,\h\h
this is how there's progress in dhamma", basically\h
just what you described. Now, that whole same\h\h
principle applies even if you do not break any\h
of the precepts that have been formulated, but as\h\h
we said, at some point you want to keep that same\h
attitude until even on the level of the thoughts\h\h
that you welcome and delight in, or the things that\h
you anticipate, at some point it will come to that.\h\h
And then you say: "Wait, I don't want to delight\h
in it, I don't want to welcome it" and yes, then\h\h
there are certain discourses that deal with how\h
to remove obstructing thoughts and that's going\h\h
to be a whole separate discussion, because\h
thoughts can arise on their own, so you have to\h\h
endure, but at some point you will also recognize:\h
"Wait, I'm actually now feeding those thoughts" and\h\h
that you should stop. And we can call it "thought",\h
but there's further development\h\h
there. But we can discuss that perhaps on another\h
occasion. But all of that will depend on\h\h
understanding what we're saying now, because\h
it's essentially for the mind not different than\h\h
when you started with the precepts for the body\h
and speech, which is why it's a gradual training.